A Guide to the Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files, 1943-1945
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files 1943-1945
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/1/2.541
This collection consists of ca. 10,500 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions may apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred on 22 March 1954.
Scope and Content Information
These files constitute the major record series generated by the president of the University of Virginia. The records consist chiefly of correspondence, but also include reports, minutes, clippings, memoranda, and related papers concerning all areas of business of the president's office.
Organization
SUB-SERIES I: General Files, 1943-1944 Boxes 1-12
SUB-SERIES II: General Files, 1945 Boxes 13-21
Contents List
- SUB-SERIES I: General Files, 1943-1944
  - "A" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Aeronautics 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--Class Managers 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--General Correspondence 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--Office 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - American Council on Education 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Ancient Languages 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Architects and Engineers 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Art and Architecture 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Art Commission--Bolivar Portrait; Alderman Bust--Keck 1943-1944 (Box 1-a)
  - Association of American Colleges 1943-1944 (Box 1-a)
  - Astronomy 1943-1944 (Box 1-a)
  - Athletics 1943-1944 (Box 1-a)
  - "B" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 1-a)
  - Biology 1943-1944 (Box 1-a)
  - Biology--Blandy Farm--contains monthly reports 1943-1944 (Box 1-a)
  - Biology--Mountain Lake 1943-1944 (Box 1-a)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Cafeteria and Dining Hall--Commons 1943-1944 (Box 1-a)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Several 1943 (Box 1-a)
  - Building Program--(general sites of future buildings discussed) 1943-1944 (Box 1-a)
  - Building Program--Nurses Home 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Building Program--Site Plan 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Bursar's Office 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - "C" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Carnegie Corporation 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Catalogues 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Chemistry 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Cocke's Biography 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Church Society for College Work 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Committees 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Committee--(emergency) Displaced Foreign Students 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Committee--Local Building 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Committee--New Buildings 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Committee--on Non-Virginia Fees 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Commons (includes correspondence with the Navy concerning use of commons) 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - "D" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Dean Ferguson (correspondence re--curriculum reorganization and the acceleration of programs) 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Dean Finley 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Dean Lewis (information re--V-12 program, repayment of Honor Loan Fund, reopening of fraternities with new rules--concerning women, absences from class, rushing, and appointment of policemen and night-watchmen) 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - "E" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Economics 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Education--General 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Education--Graduate 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Education--Nursing 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Endowment--including Alumni Board of Trustees Records 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Engineering 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - English 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - Extension Division--General (P.O.W. correspondence school program; history of the extension division) 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - "F" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - Faculty 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - Faculty--Instructors and Assistants 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - Fellowships and Endowments--William A. Smith Memorial 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - Finals (2 folders) 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - Foreign Affairs 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - Forestry 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - Forestry (Seward Forest) 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - Founder's Day--speech--"Thomas Jefferson--in Memoriam," by C. A. Beard; portrait of Simon Bolivar presented 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - "G" Miscellaneous (Wilson Gee summarizes his ideas concerning the service of the U. of VA to the State of Virginia) 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - General Education Board 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - Geology 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - Geological Survey 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - Germanic Languages 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - Gifts to the University 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - Governor's Office (2 folders) 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - "H" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - History--Corcoran School of 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - Honor System (receives $10,000 bequest from a student who had been expelled) 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - Honors Courses 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - "I" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - Insurance--TIAA, Travelers 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - International Cooperative Commission 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - Invitations 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - Institute of Public Affairs--Revival 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - Institute of International Education 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - "J" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - Jefferson Memorial Foundation 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - Jefferson Bicentennial--Alvin Barkley Speech 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - "K" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - "L" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - Law Department (2 folders) 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - Lectures--Religion 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - Lectures--Page-Barbour 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - Legal Matters (W. A. Perkins, atty) 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - Library (2 folders) 1943-1944 (Box 7)
  - McIntire Fund 1943-1944 (Box 7)
  - McGregor Library 1943-1944 (Box 7)
  - Library--Taylor Room 1943-1944 (Box 7)
  - "M" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 7)
  - Madison Hall 1943-1944 (Box 7)
  - Mary Washington College 1943-1944 (Box 7)
  - Mathematics 1943-1944 (Box 7)
  - Medical Department 1943-1944 (Box 7)
  - Medical Department--Hospital 1943-1944 (Box 7)
  - Medical Department--Ward Patients 1943-1944 (Box 8)
  - Medical Department--Student Health 1943-1944 (Box 8)
  - Military Government, School of 1943-1944 (Box 8)
  - Museum of Science 1943-1944 (Box 8)
  - Music 1943-1944 (Box 8)
  - "N" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 8)
  - National Association of State Universities 1943-1944 (Box 8)
  - Noell Bill 1943-1944 (Box 9)
  - "O" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 9)
  - "P" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 9)
  - Personnel 1943-1944 (Box 9)
  - Personnel--Retirement Plan 1943-1944 (Box 9)
  - Philosophy 1943-1944 (Box 9)
  - Physics 1943-1944 (Box 9)
  - Political Science 1943-1944 (Box 9)
  - Post-War Education Committee (not local) 1943-1944 (Box 9)
  - Post-War University (College) Committee Reports 1943-1944 (Box 9)
  - Psychology 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - Public Administration--Bureau of (includes Annual Report) 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - Public Speaking 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - Publicity 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - "Q" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - Questionnaires 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - "R" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - Recommendation, Letters of 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - Religion 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - Requisitions 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - Research--Bureau of Population and Economic Research 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - Research--Institute for Research in the Social Sciences 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - Research--League of Virginia Counties--County Government Clinic 1943-1944 (Box 10)
  - Romance Languages 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - Rural Social Economics (Fulmer, John L.) 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - "S" Miscellaneous (2 folders) 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - Senate (Minutes) 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - Sigma Xi 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - Sociology 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - State Board of Education 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - Statistics 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - Stettinius, Edward 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - Summer Session 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - Surplus Property 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - "T" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - Taylor, Mrs. R. C. 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - Town Meeting of the Air 1943-1944 (Box 11)
  - Tunstall, Robert B. 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - "U" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - University in the War 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - "V" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - Veterans Administration 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - Virginia Quarterly Review 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - Visitors--Correspondence (2 folders) 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - Visitors--Dockets, Minutes, and Memorandum 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - "W" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - Women, Dean of 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - Woodrow Wilson Birthplace Foundation 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - "X-Y-Z" Miscellaneous 1943-1944 (Box 12)
- SUB-SERIES II: General Files, 1945
  - "A" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 13)
  - Alumni Office 1945 (Box 13)
  - Alumni Office--Alumni Fund, Class Managers, Bulletin 1945 (Box 13)
  - Alumni Office--Alumni Fund--Council 1945 (Box 13)
  - Alumni Office--Alumni Fund--Gifts 1945 (Box 13)
  - Annual Reports 1945 (Box 13)
  - Applications for Positions 1945 (Box 13)
  - Art and Architecture 1945 (Box 13)
  - Art Commission 1945 (Box 13)
  - Association of American Colleges 1945 (Box 13)
  - Association of American Universities 1945 (Box 13)
  - Astronomy 1945 (Box 13)
  - Athletics 1945 (Box 13)
  - "B" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 13)
  - Biblical History and Literature 1945 (Box 13)
  - Biology 1945 (Box 13)
  - Biology--Blandy Farm (contains a history of the farm) 1945 (Box 13)
  - Buildings and Grounds--General 1945 (Box 13)
  - Buildings and Grounds--General--Cemeteries 1945 (Box 13)
  - Buildings and Grounds--General--Commons 1945 (Box 13)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Emergency Housing--General 1945 (Box 13)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Emergency Housing--Federal Public Housing 1945 (Box 13)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Fraternity Houses 1945 (Box 13)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Fuel 1945 (Box 13)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Hospital 1945 (Box 13)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Naval Housing 1945 (Box 13)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Sewage Disposal 1945 (Box 13)
  - Building Program--General 1945 (Box 13)
  - Building Program--Cafeteria and Dining Hall 1945 (Box 13)
  - Building Program--Contracts 1945 (Box 13)
  - Building Program--Mary Washington Building 1945 (Box 13)
  - Building Program--Medical Buildings 1945 (Box 13)
  - Building Program--Men's Dormitories 1945 (Box 13)
  - Building Program--Natural Resources Building 1945 (Box 13)
  - Building Program--Naval Armory 1945 (Box 13)
  - Building Program--Nurses Home 1945 (Box 13)
  - Building Program--Rotunda Restoration 1945 (Box 13)
  - Building Program--Site Plans 1945 (Box 13)
  - Building Program--Student Activities Building 1945 (Box 15)
  - Building Program--Women's Dormitory 1945 (Box 15)
  - Bursar's Office--General (contains annual report) 1945 (Box 15)
  - Bursar's Office--Fellowships and Student Assistantships 1945 (Box 15)
  - Byrd, Senator H. F. 1945 (Box 15)
  - "C" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 15)
  - Catalogues 1945 (Box 15)
  - Carnegie Corporation for the Advancement of Teaching--General Correspondence 1945 (Box 15)
  - Carnegie Corporation for the Advancement of Teaching--Minutes of Meeting 1945 (Box 15)
  - Carnegie Corporation 1945 (Box 15)
  - Chemistry Department 1945 (Box 15)
  - Church Society for College Work 1945 (Box 15)
  - Committee--Local Building 1945 (Box 15)
  - Committee--Medical School and Hospital 1945 (Box 15)
  - Committee--Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 15)
  - Committee--New Buildings 1945 (Box 15)
  - Committee--University of VA Press 1945 (Box 15)
  - Commons (contains Navy material) 1945 (Box 15)
  - Conservation Commission (information re--new natural resources building to be built at U.Va. and to house the Forest Service and the Geological Survey) 1945 (Box 15)
  - "D" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 15)
  - Darden, C. W. 1945 (Box 15)
  - Dean Ferguson (reorganization of school since Military departed) 1945 (Box 15)
  - Dean Finley 1945 (Box 15)
  - Dean Lewis 1945 (Box 15)
  - Dean Manahan 1945 (Box 15)
  - Dean Newman 1945 (Box 16)
  - Dean of Women (attempts to have age limit for admissions changed) 1945 (Box 16)
  - "E" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 16)
  - Economics 1945 (Box 16)
  - Education--General 1945 (Box 16)
  - Education--Graduate (Endowment) 1945 (Box 16)
  - Education--Graduate (Denny School) 1945 (Box 16)
  - Education--Nursing 1945 (Box 16)
  - Endowment--Alumni Board--Contingent Fund 1945 (Box 16)
  - Endowment--Alumni Board--General Correspondence 1945 (Box 16)
  - Endowment--Alumni Board--Investments 1945 (Box 16)
  - Endowment--Alumni Board--Meetings 1945 (Box 16)
  - Endowment--Alumni Board--Treasurer 1945 (Box 16)
  - Engineering 1945 (Box 16)
  - English--Lyndon Kent School of English Literature 1945 (Box 16)
  - English--Poe School of English 1945 (Box 16)
  - Extension Department 1945 (Box 16)
  - Extension Division--Radio Uses 1945 (Box 16)
  - "F" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 16)
  - Faculty 1945 (Box 16)
  - Faculty--Instructors and Assistants 1945 (Box 16)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships--General 1945 (Box 16)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships--Rhodes 1945 (Box 16)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships--William A. Smith Memorial Scholarships 1945 (Box 16)
  - Finals 1945 (Box 16)
  - Foreign Affairs (material concerning opening of school of foreign affairs) 1945 (Box 17)
  - Forestry (Seward Forest) 1945 (Box 17)
  - Forms and Form Letters 1945 (Box 17)
  - Founder's Day 1945 (Box 17)
  - Fraternities 1945 (Box 17)
  - "G" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 17)
  - General Education Board (discussion of desegregation of police force) 1945 (Box 17)
  - Geography (dept. established) 1945 (Box 17)
  - Geology 1945 (Box 17)
  - Geological Survey 1945 (Box 17)
  - Germanic Languages 1945 (Box 17)
  - Gifts to the University 1945 (Box 17)
  - Governor's Office 1945 (Box 17)
  - Graduate Dept. 1945 (Box 17)
  - "H" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 17)
  - History 1945 (Box 17)
  - "I" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 17)
  - Institute of International Education 1945 (Box 17)
  - Institute of Public Affairs 1945 (Box 17)
  - Insurance--TIAA and Blue Cross 1945 (Box 17)
  - "J" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 17)
  - Jefferson Memorial Foundation 1945 (Box 17)
  - Jefferson Memorial Foundation--Park Commission 1945 (Box 17)
  - "K" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 18)
  - "L" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 18)
  - Law Department (discussion of needs include library, housing, a Professor of International Law, Legal Medicine course) 1945 (Box 18)
  - Legal Matters 1945 (Box 18)
  - Library--General 1945 (Box 18)
  - Library--Board of Alderman 1945 (Box 18)
  - Library--McGregor Library 1945 (Box 18)
  - Library--Taylor Room (building of room) 1945 (Box 18)
  - "M" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 18)
  - McIntire Fund 1945 (Box 18)
  - Madison Hall 1945 (Box 18)
  - Mary Washington 1945 (Box 18)
  - Mary Washington Dockets 1945 (Box 18)
  - Mary Washington Reports 1945 (Box 18)
  - Medical Department--Hospital 1945 (Box 18)
  - Medical Department--Medical Compensation 1945 (Box 19)
  - Medical Department--Medical Compensation--Copies of Papers 1945 (Box 19)
  - Medical Department--Medical School 1945 (Box 19)
  - Medical Department--School of Nursing 1945 (Box 19)
  - Medical Department--Student Health 1945 (Box 19)
  - Medical Department--Ward Patient Reports 1945 (Box 19)
  - National Association of State Universities 1945 (Box 19)
  - National Association of State Universities--Committee on Accrediting 1945 (Box 19)
  - National Education Association 1945 (Box 19)
  - Naval ROTC 1945 (Box 19)
  - Naval ROTC--printed and mimeographed communications 1945 (Box 19)
  - "O" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 19)
  - "P" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 19)
  - Patent Infringements 1945 (Box 19)
  - Personnel 1945 (Box 19)
  - Phi Beta Kappa 1945 (Box 19)
  - Philosophy 1945 (Box 19)
  - Physical Education 1945 (Box 19)
  - Physics 1945 (Box 19)
  - Political Science 1945 (Box 20)
  - Post-War Education Committee 1945 (Box 20)
  - Psychology 1945 (Box 20)
  - Publications and Clippings 1945 (Box 20)
  - Public Speaking 1945 (Box 20)
  - "Q" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 20)
  - "R" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 20)
  - Radio Committee 1945 (Box 20)
  - Recommendation, Letters of 1945 (Box 20)
  - Rent Control 1945 (Box 20)
  - Requisitions 1945 (Box 20)
  - Research--General 1945 (Box 20)
  - Research--Bureau of Population and Economic Research 1945 (Box 20)
  - Research--Bureau of Population and Economic Research (Miscellaneous printed bulletins) 1945 (Box 20)
  - Research--Bureau of Administration 1945 (Box 20)
  - Research--Bureau of Administration (printed reports, etc.) 1945 (Box 20)
  - Research--League of Virginia Counties 1945 (Box 20)
  - Research--Institute for Research in the Social Sciences 1945 (Box 20)
  - Research--Richmond University Center 1945 (Box 20)
  - Romance Languages 1945 (Box 20)
  - Rural Social Economics 1945 (Box 21)
  - "S" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 21)
  - Scholarships (see Fellowships and Scholarships) 1945 (Box 21)
  - Sigma Xi 1945 (Box 21)
  - Sociology 1945 (Box 21)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools 1945 (Box 21)
  - Southern University Conference 1945 (Box 21)
  - State Board of Education 1945 (Box 21)
  - Statistics 1945 (Box 21)
  - Summer Session 1945 (Box 21)
  - Surplus Property 1945 (Box 21)
  - "T" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 21)
  - Taylor, Mrs. R. C. 1945 (Box 21)
  - Tunstall, R. B. 1945 (Box 21)
  - "U" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 21)
  - United States Office of Education 1945 (Box 21)
  - University in the War (letters from Alumni and State members) 1945 (Box 21)
  - University Houses--Applications for 1945 (Box 21)
  - "V" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 21)
  - Veterans 1945 (Box 21)
  - Veterans (printed and mimeographed material) 1945 (Box 21)
  - Virginia Education Association 1945 (Box 21)
  - Virginia Quarterly Review 1945 (Box 21)
  - Virginia State Chamber of Commerce 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Correspondence 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mr. Anderson 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mr. Black 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Senator Bustard 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mrs. Calcott 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mr. Carrington 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mr. Corbitt 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Dr. Emmett 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mr. Garnett 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mr. Goolrick 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mr. Laneaster 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mr. Stettinius 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Dr. Trout 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mrs. Wailes 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mr. Lewis C. Williams 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mr. R. Gray Williams 1945 (Box 21)
  - Visitors--Mrs. Willis 1945 (Box 21)
  - "W" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 21)
  - Woodrow Wilson Birthplace Foundation 1945 (Box 21)
  - "X-Y" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 21)
  - "Z" Miscellaneous 1945 (Box 21)